<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

To use the functions in this chapter the user must load UNDER CONSTRUCTION (so far these functions are part of affine.g). The packages 4ti2Interface, NormalizInterface and SingularInterface are required.


<Section>
    <Heading>
        Defining affine semigroups
    </Heading>

    An affine semigroup <M>S</M> is a finitely generated cancellative monoid that is reduced (no units other than 0) and is torsion-free (<M> a s= b s</M> implies <M>a=b</M>, with <M>a,b\in \mathbb N</M> and <M>s\in S</M>). 

    Up to isomorphisms any affine semigroup can ve viewed as a finitely generated submonoid of <M>\mathbb N^k</M> for some positive integer <M>k</M>. Thus affine semigroups are a natural generalization of numerical semigroups.

    The most common way to give an affine semigroup is by any of its systems of generators. As for numerical semigroups, any affine semigroup admits a unique minimal system of generators. A system of generators can be represented as a list of lists of nonnegative integers; all lists in the list having the same length (a matrix actually).  

    If <M>G</M> is a subgroup of <M>\mathbb Z^k</M>, then <M>S=G\cap \mathbb N^k</M> is an affine semigroup (these semigroups are call full affine semigroups). As <M>G</M> can be represented by its defining equations (homogeneous and evenetualy some of them in congruences), we can represent <M>S</M> by the defining equations of <M>G</M>; indeed <M>S</M> is just the set of nonnegative solutions of this system of equations. We can represent the equations as a list of lists of integers, all with the same length. Every list is a row of the matrix of coefficiens of the system of equations. For the equations in congruences, if we arrange them so that they are the first ones in the list, we provide the corresponding moduli in a list. So for instance, the equations <M>x+y\equiv 0\bmod 2,\ x-2y=0</M> will be represented as [[1,1],[1,-2]] and the moduli [2].

    <ManSection>

        <Func Arg="ls, m" Name="HilbertBasisOfSystemOfHomogeneousEquations"></Func>
        <Description>
            <A>ls</A> is a list of lists of integers and <A>m</A> a list of integers. The elements of <A>ls</A> represent the rows of a matrix <M>A</M>.  
            The output is a minimal generating system (Hilbert basis) of the set of nonnegative integer solutions of the sytem <M>Ax=0</M> where the <M>k</M> first equations are in the congruences modulo <A>m[i]</A>, with <M>k</M> the length of <A>m</A>.

            <Example><![CDATA[
gap> HilbertBasisOfSystemOfHomogeneousEquations([[1,0,1],[0,1,-1]],[2]);
[ [ 2, 0, 0 ], [ 1, 1, 1 ], [ 0, 2, 2 ] ]
]]></Example>
         </Description>
    </ManSection>

If <M>C</M> is a pointed cone (a cone in <M>\mathbb Q^k</M> not containing lines and <M>0\in C</M>), then <M>S=C\cap \mathbb N^k</M> is an affine semigroup (known as normal affine semigroup). So another way to give an affine semigroup is by a set of homogeneous inequalities, and we can represent these inequalities by its coefficients. If we put them in a matrix <M>S</M> can be defined as the set of nonnegative integer solutions to <M>Ax\ge 0</M>.

    <ManSection>

        <Func Arg="ls" Name="HilbertBasisOfSystemOfHomogeneousInequalities"></Func>
        <Description>
            <A>ls</A> is a list of lists of integers. The elements of <A>ls</A> represent the rows of a matrix <M>A</M>.  
            The output is a minimal generating system (Hilbert basis) of the set of nonnegative integer solutions to  <M>Ax\ge 0</M>.

            <Example><![CDATA[
gap> HilbertBasisOfSystemOfHomogeneousInequalities([[2,-3],[0,1]]);
[ [ 1, 0 ], [ 2, 1 ], [ 3, 2 ] ]
]]></Example>
         </Description>
    </ManSection>


</Section>

