<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Section>
 <Label Name="sc:generalized-gorenstein" />
                <Heading>
                    Several approaches generalizing the concept of symmetry
                </Heading>


Let <M>S</M> be a numerical semigroup and let <M>R</M> be its semigroup ring <M>K[\![S]\!]</M>. We say that <M>S</M> has the generalized Gorenstein property if its semigroup ring has this property. For the definition and characterization of generalized Gorenstein rings please see <Cite Key="G-I-K-T"></Cite>. 
<P/>

A numerical semigroup is said to be nearly Gorenstein if its maximal ideal is contained in its trace ideal <Cite Key="trace-canonical"></Cite>. Every almost symmetric numerical semigroup is nearly Gorenstein. 

<P/>
A numerical semigroup <M>S</M> with canonical ideal <M>K</M> is a generalized almost symmetric numerical semigroup if either <M>2K=K</M> (symmetric) or <M>2K\setminus K=\{\textrm{F}(S)-x_1,\dots, \textrm{F}(S)-x_r,\textrm{F}(S)\}</M> for some <M>x_1,\dots,x_r \in M\setminus 2M</M> (minimal generators) and <M>x_i-x_j\not\in (S-M)\setminus S</M> (not pseudo-Frobenius numbers), see <Cite Key="gas-semigroups"/>. As expected, every almost symmetric numerical semigroup is a generalized almost symmetric numerical semigroup.

<ManSection>
    <Prop Arg="s" Name="IsGeneralizedGorenstein"></Prop>
    <Description>
        <A>s</A> is a numerical semigroup.  The output is <C>true</C> if the semigroup ring <M>K[\![S]\!]</M> is generalized Gorenstein using the characterization by Goto-Kumashiro <Cite Key="G-K"></Cite>. 
        <Example><![CDATA[
gap> s:=NumericalSemigroup(3,7,8);;
gap> IsAlmostSymmetric(s);
false
gap> IsGeneralizedGorenstein(s);
true
]]></Example>
    </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
    <Prop Arg="s" Name="IsNearlyGorenstein"></Prop>
    <Description>
        <A>s</A> is a numerical semigroup.  The output is <C>true</C> if the semigroup is nearly Gorenstein, and <C>false</C> otherwise. 
        <Example><![CDATA[
gap> s:=NumericalSemigroup(10,11,12,25);;
gap> IsAlmostSymmetric(s);
false
gap> IsNearlyGorenstein(s);
true
gap> s:=NumericalSemigroup(3,7,8);;
gap> IsNearlyGorenstein(s);
false
]]></Example>
    </Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
    <Oper Arg="s" Name="NearlyGorensteinVectors"></Oper>
    <Description>
        <A>s</A> is a numerical semigroup.  
        The output is a lists of lists (making the cartesian product of them yields all possible NG-vectors). If <M>n_i</M> is the ith 
        generator of <A>s</A>, in the ith position of the list it returns all pseudo-Frobenius numbers <M>f</M> of <A>s</A> such that 
        <M>n_i+f-f'</M> is in <A>s</A> for all <M>f</M> a pseudo-Frobenius number of <A>s</A>, <Cite Key="nearly-almost"></Cite>.
        <Example><![CDATA[
gap> s:=NumericalSemigroup(10,11,12,25);;
gap> IsAlmostSymmetric(s);
false
gap> IsNearlyGorenstein(s);
true
gap> s:=NumericalSemigroup(3,7,8);;
gap> IsNearlyGorenstein(s);
false
]]></Example>
    </Description>
</ManSection>



<ManSection>
    <Prop Arg="s" Name="IsGeneralizedAlmostSymmetric"></Prop>
    <Description>
        <A>s</A> is a numerical semigroup.  Determines whether or not <A>s</A> is a generalized almost symmetric numerical semigroup. 
        <Example><![CDATA[
gap> s:=NumericalSemigroup(9, 24, 39, 43, 77);;
gap> IsGeneralizedAlmostSymmetric(s);
true
gap> IsAlmostSymmetric(s);
false
]]></Example>
    </Description>
</ManSection>




</Section>
